[Music]
hey folks welcome to the Dark Horse
podcast this is the Q & A with Yuri
Dagon who many of you hopefully most of
you have seen on my original discussion
with him about the lab leak hypothesis
for the origin of SARS Cove - the cause
of the kovat nineteen pandemic our plan
here is to have you give us questions
super chat questions will be prioritized
we're looking for high quality questions
and questions only related to the topic
in our discussion of the lab leak
hypothesis so you can ask us about other
things mentioned there but no general
questions if you would URI welcome to
the Dark Horse podcast again a lot of
people were fascinated by our discussion
and I think it is having an effect in
the world people are waking up to the
idea that they cannot just simply
dismiss this hypothesis no matter how
much that is their desire it's great in
the world yeah I would agree with that
on the other hand I would say I don't
think the two are unrelated and because
of that we cannot afford to focus in one
place and ignore the other so certainly
here in the US we are seeing unrest of a
kind that is I think in almost every way
unprecedented and that unrest is
obviously related to the the lockdown in
the sense that it changed people's
obligations in the world it caused them
to be more frustrated as the economy
began to take its descent and so to the
extent that that unrest of this scale
can happen in a country
that is among the most stable in the
world to the extent that that can be
affected by a pandemic that could emerge
at any time understanding what the roots
of that pandemic are is paramount we
can't afford to have something throw us
into chaos if that something is is
preventable so in any case I do think
you're right people are much more
focused on other topics but I don't
really see it as other topics it is that
all right so how about we start with a
couple of questions that came in during
the initial premiere of our original
discussion the first one is not about
the coronavirus per se but it is this am
i right that the glitchy computers
conspiracy from your talk with Yuri
Dagon was a joke if not how do you
assess the probability that it was a
that it wasn't a coincidence Thanks you
want to start with that I mean I think
it's mostly a coincidence because it
hasn't believed occurred and I just as
soon as I started having problems
completely wiped out of the system and
restore backup and the fact that it
hasn't happened since at least to me
probably just a coincidence the fact
that it happened with some other people
who are also involved with questioning
kind of lab leak hypothesis it could
also be a coincidence but wait wait I
think we're like half jokingly discuss
it and put out feelers into the kind of
the ether to see if there are other
people experiencing something like this
then you know for me as we I think
alluded to originally if we hear about
more people having some kind of
technical issues or any other kind of
weird things happening in their life you
know that could start being to pattern
but at this point it's just this I'm
going to take a slightly different tack
on the
question I think one has to behave as if
it is a coincidence and it is almost
impossible to rule that out unless
somebody sends you an unambiguous
message but you had a malware problem
that took oh yeah go ahead sorry I did
start getting we see to start getting
start receiving a lot of like weird you
know phishing emails almost much much
higher number of them probably just
started like a couple month back I never
opened them but sure well there's the
possibility that people were eagerly
trying to figure out what was on your
machine there's a possibility that they
were trying to spook you and there's a
possibility that it was unrelated and
just a feature of the world as it exists
but I would say we had collapses of our
system here related to the podcast that
were very unusual at a technical level
in other words we had collapses that
continued to plague us even though we
had literally swapped out every
component that could conceivably cause
it so that's an unusual pattern when
when one is troubleshooting does it mean
anything I don't know I do know that the
timing was conspicuous but of course
coincidence coincidences happen of their
own accord
and what I would say is if you're going
to find yourself in a realm like this
where you have you know essentially some
huge range of actors has an interest in
this story people want to blame China
China doesn't want to be blamed lots of
people have turned this into a political
football and they have interests in how
it is understood and so there's no
shortage of people who might want to
dissuade people like you and me who
won't look away from the story but one
can't assume that every hiccup is that
and in fact we had a hiccup at the end
of our conversation which I think you
and I both read as very unlikely to me
anything why would you disrupt the end
of a stream but I've had streams
disrupted at moments that were very
conspicuous before and it started to
happen I had one the most amazing set of
collapses we had was right after I first
started talking about your medium piece
and its implications so I don't know
what to make of all this again I think
one has to work from the assumption that
this is an organic problem in a highly
complex technological world in which
lots of pieces that are made by
different different people are
interfacing together that's you know
that's a bug prone world but there's
also a lot that's conspicuous about the
pattern and because we all have a
history of facing technical glitches in
our computing lives when something
really out of the ordinary happens it
does have a different feel yep all right
yep let's leave it at that the next
question is if the virus had escaped
from her lab why would she jangly
release the sequence for our ATG 13 and
placed more suspicion on her lab and
then the second part of the question is
how do we explain the samples and
original patients with exposure at the
Hunan seafood market you're probably in
the best position to answer this earring
well let's let's try let's just address
the first point first I wasn't very
clear on the second one let's address
the first one so why would she generally
kind of release the ATG sequence rather
than just I guess keep being silent well
the first and foremost she already
released part of that sequence back in
2016 I guess I mean she collected it in
2013 but they had a publication in 2016
where they released a threat I went to
the sequence to gene bank and so
actually by the time she generally
released it in 2012
the full secret of the full genome they
were already groups I think with the
print print or just maybe some comments
on biology blog somewhere who identified
that very fragment and they were
essentially kind of on the trail she's
usually saying this is the closest
relative of stars to that we were able
to find using you know the blasting of
genomic sequences in the database so
unless she kind of release the full she
basically she would be made to release
the false you know anyway so it's I
think it's much better for her to do it
proactively rather than wait for you
know some comfortable questions
and secondly she could of course release
the the sequence that she most you know
would be most favorable with again I'm
not saying she's trying to doctor than
any in any way home but it's a
possibility so maybe she was trying to
she could have been trying to divert the
attention of the people to from the you
know maybe a closer sequence they have
in their possession by using the the
fragment that she already released in
the G Bank years ago and then building
around it with a four percent difference
from the current starts to genome but I
mean she it's not like she had an option
of just staying silent was precisely
because she sure you made know that they
had the closest fragment yeah I agree
with this analysis she didn't have a
choice
that it was the I mean if this had been
an escape from her lab and she is aware
of that fact that's a big if but if
that's what happened and for whatever
reason she was hoping that that would
not be the conclusion of the scientific
community she had very little choice but
to to release the sequence and as we
talked about in our earlier discussion
there's also the question about is there
something about the four nine nine one
strain
that is connected to something in
possibly the database that was deleted
that was very conspicuous and by
releasing it as if it was a separate
strain that it might lead people in a
different direction
again this is speculative we're not
saying this did happen we're not saying
we know but we're saying this is not
behavior that suggests that this person
is necessarily trying to shed light on
what happened if you know let's take the
possibility that the Chinese government
has exerted pressure and said we don't
want this understood it could be that
she's doing this under duress so there
are lots of possibilities but there's I
don't see anything exonerating in her
releasing that sequence right and also I
think she released it after there was
this Indian reprint that alleged some
small fragments from the HIV genome
being present being stars too and so
maybe that was her kind of reaction to
show that no actually those fragments
were present in their ancestral strain
or like the close relative so she had to
release that ancestral strain to kind of
you know add evidence to her claims and
she seemed very upset with that Indian
preprint
the I think in WeChat or somewhere
somewhere she said that she hopes those
scientists close their stinking mouths
or something like that relating to that
very very frequent and so that could be
another another reason why she decided
to release it and also it does seem that
there is you know maybe if not panic but
to definitely someone some duress as you
said that her team is under and I'm sure
the whole is - hydrology is under and
they're getting some you know external
control from the military imposed upon
them from Beijing the major general Chen
I think she overtook leadership in
history biology and so it's not
necessarily like a cold calculated to
move it could be again just something
that they decided to do to exonerate
themselves in the eyes of
however maybe of their unit impose to
the leadership from the king they
decided to show that it's not them
finally there is another kind of line of
thinking this I agree that's a little
bit of a more conspiratorial idea that
maybe this is her kind of signaling
about some other lab whereas her
phrasing is a little bit interesting is
that she says she swears on her life
that it didn't come from her lab so this
kind of opens leafs opens the
possibility that it could have come from
some other lab and she might know but
she's not you know in a position to
fully say this and by releasing the
sequence she's maybe you know giving
some hints as to okay you guys figure
out what I mean exactly where this could
come from yes it would be wonderful if
that's a possibility it would be
wonderful if it if there was some
mechanism as we talked about in our
earlier discussion if there was some
mechanism that allowed people to
securely offer information that would
allow us to put together the origin
story of this this virus right so let me
ask you this and so go ahead yeah
just one final point sorry I can't keep
keep getting back to this is it's also
interesting what they didn't say and
what they didn't say is the whole back
story of anymore Nia in the in the mind
in the you know Gian where they
originally collected this RIT g13 strain
and they still I don't think they today
ever address this but there was this
outbreak of six miners forgot pneumonia
after which she generally was called to
the line and did collect the sample and
I don't think nobody from Wuhan still to
this day I've heard rest this story and
we know that they're leading kind of
SARS guy the academician Zhang I keep
his name but he's like the mr. Stars guy
he was in charge essentially of this
pneumonia investigation he actually
ordered the miner samples checked for
SARS antibodies back in 2013 and I think
they actually did the working in
the one Institute and she's yelling was
definitely in the look of this work and
since this is still not mentioned to
this day officially like in the Chinese
press or in any other scientific
publications it's definitely you know
still a big question mark but yeah yeah
as you pointed out in our last
discussion the place to pick up the
trail would be those samples if if we
had access to them yeah so anyway if the
world is trying to figure out what to do
next that would be a good bet in order
to shed more light on the story you
raised the issue of the claim that there
are sequences from HIV in SARS Cove -
and I remember when I first saw that
claim I thought no way and then I saw
some stuff that suggested to me actually
there might be and I my first reaction
was wow that would be open-and-shut case
if there were and then I remember
looking into it and realizing that it
wasn't the reason it would be an
open-and-shut case I thought was that
coronaviruses and retroviruses are so
distantly related I mean if related at
all that the transmission of sequences
from one group to the other would likely
have been accomplished technologically
but when I looked into the that claim I
remember I don't exactly remember what
the evidence was but actually I got the
sense that it would not be that
surprising and I I abandoned that that
line of thinking do you have thoughts or
information on the possibility of HIV
sequences showing up in SARS Cove -
right I along with everybody else was
you know once it was analyzed that those
actual sequences the fragments are just
very short fragments and it could have
been just essentially acquaintances that
you know pretty much any short enough
strain of letters showing up in any
other genome might be a coincidence
but I think this storyline was picked up
again by Luc montagnier a French Nobel
Prize winning scientist and he still
continues you know promoting this idea
although the mainstream scientific
mainstream is even farther from this
line of reasoning is this from the
general lab leak hypothesis but I have
to be honest I didn't really get back
into this or I didn't read his trip
although he has published a preprint
allure they seem to you know provide
more evidence so far some HIV related
genetic fragments in source code - yeah
I recall looking into his work initially
his credential is obviously based on
such powerful prior work that it's very
hard to ignore his belief that this
contains HIV fragments and that that
essentially is a smoking gun but I
remember looking into it and
mechanistically I was just not compelled
that the story added up but certainly on
the list of hypotheses I believe it on
we have to we have to analyze it
carefully and figure out whether or not
what is being claimed is sufficiently
improbable that it implies a special
origin origin explanation all right so
let's see this one seafood market yes
maybe I think the I mean at this point
we can safely rule out dude who know
seafood market as the source of the
outbreak as has been ruled out by even
you know mainstream China that's their
official position now that the virus
came into the market before it came out
of the market to use the quote
essentially because even initially
there's a slants of publication
analyzing the first patients and the
first I think three out of four patients
that were
treated in the hospital with the first
with the SARS cough - coronavirus three
of the four didn't have exported - who
knows if good work and that was kind of
the early sign that is probably not the
source of the outbreak and later on when
they analyzed samples from from that
market although there's we are very
interestingly not very many samples were
collected before the market was
completely sanitized and scrubbed but it
was still like there weren't any animal
samples off anything close to the source
code to just kind of human samples which
almost certainly were to spend time
related of people who had sorry co2
already you know picked up been chewed
out somewhere else outside of the market
and brought it in yeah I think at this
point we can rule out the market as a
source what we can say in retrospect is
that the evidence for the market is
circumstantial evidence basically of
proximity that there is no evidence of
the virus in animals in the market and
there's evidence of people who had no
connection to the market who were sick
in the first the first round and so that
effectively takes it to an extremely low
probability the interesting thing though
is that in the announcement that China
had revised its explanation and was no
longer it did no it no longer believed
that the Wuhan seafood market was the
source it also dismissed the laboratory
origin hypothesis so it sort of had this
poison pill aspect to it in which they
they were almost like negotiating with
the logic will grant you that you're
right that the Wuhan seafood market is
not involved but the lab is also not
involved with no compelling evidence of
why we should assume that now let me ask
you as long as we're here the there are
a couple of pieces of analysis floating
around about behavior in and around the
Wuhan virality Institute Wuhan Institute
of our
and hospitals in Wuhan China where there
is an anomalous behavior detected and
the claim is that these things imply
that there was awareness of an accident
in the case of the virality Institute
and that there was awareness or that
there was in a medically annales influx
of patients into the hospital I guess
this would have been October is that
right do you have any thoughts about
whether that those pieces of analysis
actually imply anything have you looked
at them I have everybody just you know
I've once then use hits I looked at the
information I think you're referring to
two kind of different sets of analysis
first being analysis of cellular signal
around the within lab that report it's
some kind of blackout period in October
I think early role so when you say
cellular you mean cellular phone
activity right mm-hmm right exactly
yes all your own activity that seems
it's a I guess publicly collected
database anonymized which is used by all
sorts of commercial intelligence
providers to analyze trends of potential
consumers so basically a lot of
companies are collecting all the
cellular data of pretty much everybody
this data can be available to these
providers who can mine it somebody mind
that data and saw that at the time of
the early October there was a sudden
drop in the usual number of cell phones
and cell phone traffic associated with
the area of the Institute's bsl-4
facility and on the basis of this they
could hypothesize with baby to signify
some kind of accidents and shutdown in
the area and also they seem to implicate
that there was some kind of traffic
shutdown because not only didn't lab
itself but the area around it the
traffic around like the the he cooler
traffic with cell phones I guess they
my head has greatly diminished for for a
period of I guess two weeks or something
saying all this from memory it's been a
while since I looked like my little bit
off on some data points so that was one
thing and it was released deccan two
months ago and since then and nobody's
really had any follow up so it kind of
died down there was no follow-up
investigation by regular intelligence
agency or anybody else and then recently
there was another circumstantial
evidence of consumer trans released
which was these first of all parking
lots around hospitals exhibiting many
more cars last fall versus default a
year previously and secondly the keyword
searches for diarrhea and fever if I run
correctly
that kind of spiked in again I think it
was October or Oh late September
something like that so they were trying
to tie that into the idea that actually
the virus circulating in Wuhan or in
hebei province is much earlier than it
was kind of officially well first of all
may be recognized and secondly just may
be realized maybe you know the hospitals
or the authorities just didn't realize
they have this kind of initial stages of
clinical and on their hands I mean it's
it's it's a valid hypothesis it's I
don't know if how strong it is because I
mean generally I guess every year we we
have all sorts of viruses around this
time and whether spike and keyboard
searches for diarrhea is indicative of
this particular strain of kind of assess
well stranger starts to being a presence
in the population that I don't know
whether it's a valid conjecture or
connection or the tube precisely because
I mean even in Russia there was a spike
in pneumonias back in November and
there's a lot of where there were at
least I don't know if there's any more
but there were a lot of getting
conjectures that maybe we Russia have
been exposed to source cough too much
previously we
we develop survey you mean immunity and
this is one of the kind of popular
people's explanation why we're not
getting the same level of pandemic back
in March as the rest of the world was
the idea was well maybe we had it in
November we didn't know this of course
then we got the same thing as the rest
of the world
maybe just a couple of weeks delayed and
that idea they don't yeah so I I had the
same same thought which is that in order
to assess especially no it's actually
true for both the cell phone data and
hospital data what one wants to do is an
analysis of if you survey an area at
random that looks something like the
Hebei province for example how often do
you see something this anomalous right
in other words would you see lots of
things that were there a viral Aegean
stitute you might think it was an
accident but there's no virality
Institute so you don't notice it so
anyway I had the same sense that the ice
was not very thick with respect to these
couple of claims that said it could be
evidence and if you found that cell
phone traffic dying down in the way that
we see it in in October around the moon
on the one Institute was a very unusual
event than it would be stronger evidence
but at this point we in the public don't
know how common these things are and so
we can't we can't assess these pieces of
data right another similar piece of data
that kind of get went uninvestigated was
this leak from US intelligence
apparently somewhere in the US
intelligence community was kind of ring
alarm bells in November that there is
already an outbreak in Wuhan that it's
gonna be serious and they see all sorts
of disruptions already in place and
supposedly this was November and this
was published in Washington Post I think
but then again it was like never follow
it up so we don't know how real that
info was why did it ultimately get
ignored
so I mean still a lot of unanswered
questions and maybe some point these
whole pieces the possible puzzle will
fit or maybe it's just kind of like
red herrings and some mr. petitioner
files leaks that we just can't have to
sit through yep okay let's move on to
the next question
next question says suppose we develop a
corona virus vaccine that with minor
tweaks could also be effective on bats
as well thoughts on dispersing in bat
populations as an extra buffer I have
some thoughts here as a bat biologist do
you want to start yeah so my first
thought is first of all as widespread as
fear of vaccination is amongst humans
it's even worse in bats and so my guess
is they just won't go along with it all
right
yet English that was a hilariously funny
joke only worth a chuckle in Russian I
guess but so it was good the I think the
real question here first of all the idea
that you would have a vaccine in humans
that works in bats it's a question of
how you would even establish that I mean
it's obviously doable but is it worth
the extra effort to figure out whether
or not you know if let's say that minor
tweaks are necessary that's not a simple
matter to figure out what those minor
tweaks are and figuring out how to
vaccinate bats and whether it has worked
is going to be a long-term project at
the very least and I think the really
important issue is the same one that
applies generally to this
gain-of-function research for the
purpose of figuring out how to prevent
pandemics which is if gain-of-function
research is more likely to produce a
pandemic than it is to give us useful
information about how to present a
prevent one then it's not a good idea
and likewise attempting to vaccinate
bats against against viruses that could
leap to humans and then could evolve
into a pandemic is probably going to
create such a increase in the intensity
of human back contact with exactly the
bats that are harboring these viruses
that I would say it's probably a losing
proposition to begin with
yeah absolutely I think you know having
some kind of that vaccination program
where it's like gene driving bets to
clear the wolf any sorts of
coronaviruses is there a good use of
people's money or time or yes and plus
my create extra dangers I think we're
just better off leaving the bats alone
just both for research purposes and
human purposes and actually I think she
gently is one was one of her missions to
stop the kind of the barbaric notion of
people eating that that was one of her
key points in her talk 20:18 like a dead
light talk she gave in China and she
actually said that this is this pandemic
is a payback for Humanity for bad manic
practices of imposing you know
disturbing wildlife so in that sense but
you know I think before we start going
vaccinating bats we have a minor issue
of not even having a human vaccine first
and this is desperately needed you know
our purpose
yeah so I agree with you the human
vaccine is obviously the priority I
think in the meantime if we just ask the
bats to social distance that's probably
the best best we can do
you know fly to wing lengths apart that
kind of thing all right next question
what concerns me most
isn't that the experts got it wrong
initially it's how adamant they were
that it couldn't be questioned or that
they couldn't be questioning I
absolutely agree with this experts are
they have to have leeway to get things
wrong and frankly even the fact of
certainty is a an indicator that
something has gone wrong there was such
a strong desire to shut down the lab
leak hypothesis to begin with that we
weren't having a scientific discussion
we were having a discussion with
scientists that was not scientific
and and as I pointed out in our
discussion earlier this creates a new
problem for us a novel one which is the
very people we need most to speak
without us doubting their credibility
have all indicted their credibility
simultaneously that really couldn't be a
more dangerous circumstance so hopefully
we can learn that lesson as painful as
it is let's learn it and never let that
happen again thank you all right
next person says in honor of the mighty
Pangolin I must say pangolins I hate
that they were implicated in this story
I'm a big fan of this creature
so yes the mighty Pangolin it's a shame
but do realize for anybody who's
thinking that penguins and bats are a
task that these viruses are parasitizing
them the same way they are parasitizing
us so the bats and the pangolins are on
our side right they didn't do this to us
okay that's a terrible joke yeah
terrible actually I had an advisor guy
named Charles Handley who was one of the
great bat biologists I was the
Smithsonian curator of mammals and he
one point after the Vietnam War I think
tried to convince the military that they
should equip and fighter jets with mist
nets so that if somebody crashed in a
jungle that they could feed themselves
on bats and in order to test that
hypothesis or the hypothesis that that
was a viable way to survive he lived for
a month that way and when I asked him
how the bats were he looked at me with
no humor in his eyes and said crunchy so
anyway that also tells you something
because I mean he the best he would have
been eating were new world bats I'm not
sure that they're harboring large
numbers of coronaviruses but certainly
this concern wasn't on anybody's mind
when he did that work so that tells you
that there are dangers hidden in plain
sight
okay next question
I'm struggling to understand what you
are talking about I am so interested and
I want to learn more thank you I
highlighted this one because I thought
it was worth giving a kind of one
paragraph summary of what you and I are
on about here why this is a focus why it
matters you want to take a crack at it
or do you want me to please so I would
say we have a pandemic it's creating a
tremendous amount of harm
there's the harm it's doing and there's
the harm that we are doing to ourselves
in an effort to stop it
the origin of that pandemic is of
tremendous importance because one it may
contain lessons about how we ended up
here that will allow us to prevent this
from happening in the future whether
those lessons are about a human behavior
like eating bush meat that causes us to
come in contact with zoonotic viruses or
whether it's about gain-of-function
research in the lab it is important that
we figure out what we did wrong so that
we stop doing it and this doesn't happen
again second thing is that to the extent
that one finds the scientific community
rallying around a point expressing a
consensus that is similar to what you
would hear around the question of does
the Earth orbit the Sun or does HIV
cause AIDS or any one of a number of
secure hypotheses when you hear that
kind of resolute consensus and then you
look at the data and you look at the
analysis and the analysis far falls
apart and the data suggests a hypothesis
is viable that has been eliminated from
the table it suggests that you have a
whole different vulnerability and that
vulnerability is in the way your
scientific apparatus functions and we
are so dependent on our scientific
apparatus being above politics and
of the market and in a position to tell
us when we are putting ourselves in
danger that even just simply detecting
that scientists are reaching a consensus
that is not justified and spreading it
as if it were that is eaten of itself a
problem so hear me very clearly even if
it turns out that this virus jumped from
the wild and got into the human
population evolved the ability to jump
from one person to the next and spread
across the globe and the implication of
a lab leak is false even if that turns
out to be the case the consensus that
scientists reached was not justified
even if they turn out to have been right
the consensus and their certainty around
it was not justified and that is in and
of itself an existential threat because
we need the natural disagreement between
scientists to tell us what possibilities
surround us we don't need false
consensus we need frankness and that's a
tough lesson but I think it's an
important one to remember anything to
add thank you
all right so let's see next one this
person just a comment they say a Chimera
virus sounds scary downlighting of
downloading a virus is scary I would
certainly agree the ability to download
a sequence that we know is infectious
and then effectively leave it on the
honor system that no one will release it
that's a terrifying level of power right
so today implied downloading being able
to print DNA yep I think they're going
from what you said that you could you
could get these things printed at a lot
of different locations you said
something about there being places in
China that would do it very cheaply I
mean it's definitely printing is very
cheap but it's not it's not like anybody
could do it you actually do biology lab
you have to stitch those pieces together
and put it in live culture I mean you
could do it in the homeland garage don't
get me wrong it doesn't require
different to setup from just a garage
did do we do it yourself facility but
hopefully if you're you know ordering
virus parts online or through any kind
of provider there is some kind of
screening process that sets off alarm
bells you know you wouldn't be able to
just like a bioterrorist wouldn't be
good without anybody Authority the
tracking got down
but state actors yeah you could so are
you suggesting that at the moment those
checks exist so that only a state level
actor or something like it I know they
exist in the States if you were large
enough fragment of any particular known
pathogen yummy you could try to probably
try to circumvent that if you tried but
I think it specially after this pandemic
there's very close watches and usually
they're the people printing this stuff
they they kind of know where this is
coming have enough biology not knowledge
few people doing wait a minute why does
he need you know this particular class
we printed this particular fragment
anyway so on one level it's already
being kind of countered by various
intelligence agencies at least in the
States
on the other hand I think after this
pandemic as we alluded to an original
podcast you might get like new entrants
new terrorists like looking at this
realizing how how easy it is why why
kitchen impact they can have 4,000
Congress dollars yep then they hope not
hopefully yeah I hope not too but I
really think hoping not it doesn't work
what works is recognizing that this
danger is out there and figuring out how
to make it inaccessible because you know
the very nature of terrorists terrorism
happens when people are not powerful
enough to cause a change that they want
to cause for whatever reason and so they
seek some sort of power amplifier that
functions through terror and certainly
the relatively low price point for a
huge amount of havoc that we now know as
possible is certain to be attractive so
that means we have to be much more
sophisticated about preventing this
because sure it's going to be out of
reach for people who are small-time
enough but people whose interests are
not honorable
exist at every scale and we can't afford
to have this in reach for those with
significant power and resources okay so
next question is an interesting one I've
heard this one a number of times do you
think it's worth finding out what
happened in China even if it ups
tensions between China and the US or the
world this could have big implications
on trade and geopolitics possibly even
lead to Wars or proxy wars thanks Ben
I'll start here I don't think we have a
choice we cannot shield an investigation
into the origins of a phenomenon that's
obviously putting a huge fraction of the
world's well-being in jeopardy
irrespective of where is leads yes it is
potentially going to lead to tensions
between China and the US and the rest of
the world on the other hand I think we
were very clear in our initial
discussion that we don't really see this
if the lab leak hypothesis is correct we
don't see this as the responsibility of
China per se this is the responsibility
of the scientific community that decided
that it was safe and desirable to engage
in gain-of-function research on that
borne coronaviruses and as terrible as
the outcome is I believe if the lab leak
hypothesis is true as in the form that
we think it might well be true that that
is an honest error a spectacular one but
the blame is not what this is about so I
am concerned that the Trump
administration has sought as much as it
has opened the possibility that this
month at the lab leak hypothesis might
be real it has also politicized that
claim and made it frankly much more
difficult for those of us who wish to be
careful about this because it is seen
when one talks about this hypothesis
that they are on a political side which
is not the case so I would advise us to
solve the problem of geopolitical
tensions by being clear about the fact
that this is a matter of great interest
for humanity's well-being and that that
requires us to figure out what happened
it's not a matter of blame unless
something truly unexpected happened here
like this was an intentionally released
bioweapon that would change this dynamic
quite a bit because this would obviously
be an act of war but assuming that's not
what happened
let's let's recognize that what appears
possible and maybe likely here is an
honest scientific mistake of spectacular
proportions and it wouldn't be the first
one right absolutely
for example there's this 1937 flu
pandemic h1n1 which I think the modern
scientific consensus agrees now that it
was a lab leak from China who have been
working on some sort of vaccine for that
strain which actually at that time was
already extinct extinct I think it's the
same strain that was the Spanish flu
strain and maybe they were
just in case returns trying to create a
vaccine which actually escaped the lab
and started an outbreak first in China
and the Soviet Union around the same
area and for many years it was taboo in
scientific circles to to even
contemplate the idea that this could
have been caused by a lab leak although
there were whole works like temperature
sensitivity of the this viral strain
which is a hallmark of like vaccine
attenuation and eventually I think many
decades later it was then recognized and
acknowledged by the scientific community
yeah sorry it was a lab leak I think we
might have just very similar situation
here where as you know in the immediate
future barring some you know
whistleblowers or unexpected evidence
come out if the status quo remains
nobody's gonna acknowledge this was a
lab leak if it was or of course we are
you know operating under the assumption
that this is a lab leak if later on we
have evidence oh no actually this was a
natural outbreak and we show evidence of
these sonic animals or the intermediate
carrier then of course this question is
off the table
and it will just be proven wrong and eat
whatever but if there was a lab leak I
think were several years away if not
decades of actually the scientific
consensus acknowledging it and the state
the government's acknowledging as well
but it is interesting I think you looted
is that the American government can
stopped forcing the issue a few months
back because they were pretty aggressive
initially and then they kind of just
stopped stopped talking about and maybe
they at that point they realized that it
was a lab leak but was a leak of
research paid for by American taxpayers
so collaboration of American researchers
you know it's not a very politically
high dividend case to keep pushing so
maybe they dropped it that's why we drop
the subject
yeah I have the same sense that there
was a recognition that a story that
looked
useful suddenly became so complicated in
terms of what it implied that there was
a loss of enthusiasm on everybody's part
for talking about it which is really the
reason that we have to pursue it now
what I'm hoping is that somewhere out
there in the virality community there
are people who have the same sense that
we do that this story does not add up as
a simple zone otic Jump doesn't mean it
didn't happen but so far we don't have
enough pieces to see how it would have
and lab leak would make good sense and
they're gonna look at each other across
the table and say you know what we
actually have an obligation to say what
we understand is true and why it
suggests the map of probabilities that
we see that would be highly desirable so
hopefully hopefully they can hear how
important it is that we need viral
adjust to begin to rescue their
credibility by telling us what we don't
yet know about this story hopefully that
will happen I really I really do think
it's possible and I should say there are
a few courageous people in virology who
have very carefully indicated that this
possibility is alive and that's a very
hopeful sign so maybe we'll see more of
that as people realize that this
question is not going to go away until
it's settled all right thanks for doing
this it's unacceptable that the
scientific community is so dismissive
totally agree DNA research has come a
long way since I was reading black and
gray rectangles on an x-ray film you
better believe it I have to say I'm I'm
old enough and I studied biology in
college long enough ago that I have the
same sense of it's amazing how far we've
come and I guess the other thing I would
say on that point is these things don't
the rate of change is not consistent
fields get stuck they don't make very
interesting progress for long periods of
time and then suddenly they take a
quantum leap and so if you check back in
haphazardly sometimes you discover a
field that was sleepy has made a ton of
progress and this is part of the reason
that I said in our last discussion that
I wanted a list of all the things that
we're doing that are dangerous that I
don't yet know we're up to that I know
I'm gonna find out about after the
accident has already happened the list
of times that this has occurred since
2008 is long and I want to know what's
going to be added to the list so we can
address it ahead of time that's really
where we need to be you have anything to
add just watching himself it's sad look
to the x-ray crystallographer pictures
yeah that is a long time lapse right
it's x-ray crystallography here not just
southern blot or something okay I don't
this one that says I don't fully
understand the ethical implications of
gain-of-function tests I've heard the
concept discussed in a negative context
a few times would love to see the steel
man case made for the positive in a
future Q&A I think we can easily steal
man the case for for gain-of-function
research you want to do it
why don't you start sure
gain-of-function research allows us to
survey the capacity of viruses and and
to understand the harm they will do
ahead of time without having to actually
find these needles in a haystack out in
nature we can take things that are in
the neighborhood we can composite them
we can passage them and we can therefore
essentially see into a future that we
would have to spend a tremendous amount
more to discover in the wild and that
amount of power is potentially very
protective for humans and the only
argument against it is that we cannot
control the we cannot control the
substances that we have enhanced from
the possibility of escape but of course
humans are very capable of doing
remarkable things and figuring out how
to prevent an infectious particle from
getting out of a laboratory while it is
a difficult problem is not an unsolvable
problem that would be the steal man
argument I think now the answer is
actually that there is a related rates
problem and the more of these enhanced
viruses we produce the greater the
chances that one will escape and because
the ingredient that you cannot eliminate
from the mix is human beings who at the
moment are absolutely required at the
laboratory to do the work you cannot
eliminate human error and if you cannot
eliminate human error and people have to
go home to sleep and to eat and to all
the things that human beings do when
they're off the clock you cannot prevent
a leak so it may be that the chances of
creating a pandemic simply outstrip the
chances of preventing one if we're going
to do this research I will say as a
final piece I did suggest in a prior
discussion
that if you were going to insist on
doing this research and I'm not sure
that we need to do this research I think
it may be the best defense maybe
limiting unnecessary and dangerous
contact with wildlife but if you're
hell-bent on doing this research then
maybe you should be doing it on a ship
right out at sea a fit that when
something escapes can be quarantined
from the rest of the world so that we
don't run into this problem again and if
you think that's too much hassle then I
think you have it understood how much
danger we're putting ourselves in long
expeditions don't go out and study some
marine life and you can to join
expedition with isolated bsl-4 based on
three facility on that ship I mean it's
definitely gonna decrease the number of
people willing to do this research oh
yeah nobody snuck ownership for a few
months but but if the argument yeah if
the argument is that we have to do this
research then how much do you have to
pay somebody to live on a ship to do it
sorry I didn't mean to interrupt you
it's a good point I don't know if I
subscribe to that argument I don't
really see the does this logic that we
have we are gating again actually from
this function research excuse the pun
because we're trying to I don't know
what predict a pandemic by trying to
recreate in a lab one of the trillions
of mutations that might or might not
happen in nature and then and then do
what we create as the black lab and
other labs are trying to do Panther the
virus vaccine or to the punic well first
of all I don't know IFIF the numbers are
in in our favor because we can't
obviously recreate all the mutations
that are my possible in nature might be
possible in nature that might actually
jump over into human
and trying to do so I think creates
higher risk of having it in a lab rather
than actually being able to prevent it
by using this approach and secondly
obviously well in this case we did get a
functionary so if you didn't help us
come up with any Panther in the virus
vaccine a therapeutic in time which I
think they worked on 10 years maybe more
so and again you probably don't even
need gain-of-function research to work
on a panther a virus vaccine you can
just take the existing known strains and
work on those rather than trying to make
so yeah I agree I agree with all of what
you've said and I would add a couple
things one if it turns out to be a lab
leak then we know that the very people
who were telling us that we needed to
educate ourselves about what an enhanced
virus could and would do because that
would be protective when it came down to
it didn't tell us what they had learned
in other words as I've been saying
repeatedly part of what may be going on
here is that this virus is adapted to
laboratory conditions some of them
intentionally imposed and some of them
quite accidental so if it is true that
this research is supposed to armed us
with knowledge in order to better
protect ourselves but the knowledge
isn't forthcoming at the point that the
thing escapes the lab then that would
suggest that the whole thing was a waste
so that logic doesn't apply if this
truly didn't come from a lab but if it
did I think we have to look very
carefully at it the last thing I would
say is as a bat biologist I worked for
years with bats I captured them I glued
transmitters on them I followed them
around the forest and at the time it was
not well understood that there were
these very dangerous viruses that we
might be coming in close contact with
now the reason that I mentioned this is
that I was not alone in doing this kind
of work there are tens of thousands of
people
wild creatures handling them and there
is a famous instance of a fungus that is
being transmitted to amphibians the
danger didn't go to humans it went to an
fib ian's
through humans but it is not the case
that all of these people who are working
on an indefinitely large number of
species in the wild are constantly
creating zoonotic pandemics could it
happen sure but I think what those who
are arguing that we need
gain-of-function research to address the
possibility of a zoonotic jump are
ignoring is that human contact with
wildlife is very ancient and very
widespread we have lots of diseases that
have jumped through agriculture for
example but it may be much less
dangerous having casual contact with
animals in the wild than we are being
led to believe
and the real protection probably comes
from preventing intense contact like the
butchering of wild animals the
butchering of wild animals obviously
exposes people to bodily fluids of these
animals and that is a very high
likelihood of something jumping which
still doesn't make for a pandemic
because in general if something jumps in
such an instance it will die out before
it finds the magic the evolutionary
magic for transmitting between people
but you know we have hiv/aids which we
think came from a chimpanzee probably
one butchered in the bush meat trade so
that's a major indication that bush meat
it's not such a hot idea but the amount
of contact is high already
the number of zoonotic jumps that have
caused a pandemic from scientific
research that is not gain-of-function in
nature is very low if not zero I don't
know of a case maybe somebody will alert
us to one but I think we've we've been
we've been falsely led to the belief the
chances that casual contact will cause a
pandemic is much higher than it actually
is
and the research has been portrayed
is much safer than it actually is okay
all right we are at one hour let's get
through some more of these questions all
right here's our just oh sure add a
final note to that question I think you
were referring to Peter - like who's
trying to make a case that these jumps
happen in regular basis and I was using
one of his flawed papers where they saw
six farmers being affected not affected
to carry antibodies for particular
strain of that kernel virus I like 218
people to justify his number yet there's
like a million to seven million farmers
in Southeast Asia were exposed to these
zoning jumps but and I think yeah that's
really correct and finally I think as we
mentioned in the original broadcast or a
signage I think it's a much better way
to spend the money spent on
gain-of-function research to spend it on
tracing of various editing outbreaks
that happened I will cross the world to
be able to very quickly identify such
epidemics and these days the cost of
full genomic sequencing you know you
could sequence the virus viral strain
pretty cheaply and pretty quickly it's
so cheap now that you know whereas it
wasn't ten years ago so ten years ago
you could you know make any case that we
need to be prepared but these days we
can actually very quickly in real time
find what exactly is causing a small
outbreak a big outbreak and you can get
the genomic sequences of all the virus
viruses making a new appearance or
confirming this is a new virus it's a
new outbreak where this is like no same
seasonal kernel i restrain or influenza
strain pretty quickly pretty chick with
cheap weight or a very distributed scale
all across the world and I think this is
what we need to invest as the global
society into at this point much better I
think will give us much better outcome
get a functional research yeah III
at that point and I guess I would add a
couple things one I think we need some
better language the idea that is an
attic jump is a massive danger is really
covering the fact that this is two steps
synodic jumps probably do happen
regularly is it not attempts that catch
on that after they have jumped make the
evolutionary discoveries that allow them
to spread across a large population
that's probably very rare and so anyway
I think dividing those two things and
figuring out actually probabilistically
where is the place to prevent this right
it would be a better investment and then
the other thing I would say which this
has just become very clear in my mind is
that part of the problem is that we
don't take normal regular pathogens that
we're familiar with nearly seriously
enough and that there is a lot we can do
monitoring the circulation of pathogens
and interfering with their ability to
jump between people that we've only just
begun discussing in the context of kovat
19 and so I would advocate that we got
smarter about how not to transmit
pathogens to each other you know in the
same way that hygiene greatly increased
our resistance to things because we just
figured out how they were spreading and
it figured out how to stop doing it we
now have technologies at our disposal
that would allow us to prevent this from
happening in all sorts of context where
we are actually inflicting it on ourself
like our HVAC systems right we could
design HVAC systems that are excellent
at clearing viruses from buildings at
the moment lots of them just spread
these things around buildings so so
anyway there's lots of room to make
humanity safer and better that doesn't
require this high wire act of
gain-of-function research all right next
question have you interviewed a
virologist or other expert and they
suggest a Lena Chan
a couple other people I would gladly
have a virologist on I'm a fan at a
distance of dr. Chan's work I would say
in the current environment there is I
think likely to be concern even amongst
people who are like minded about what
may have happened here about talking to
anyone who is being dismissed as a
conspiracy theorist and I've tried to be
very careful conspiracy theorist is a
stigma inflicting term this is a
hypothesis it functions like any other
hypothesis it's a question of whether or
not the evidence supports the hypothesis
or not and eventually hopefully one
hypothesis will turn out to be clearly
enough supported that it then becomes
the theory it doesn't start out as a
theory but I would be I would welcome
such a person I would have URI back on
we could jointly talk to such a person
but I also understand that this is in
addition to being a very important
scientific question this is a dangerous
question to people's careers and people
will have to decide for themselves
whether or not they can afford to engage
with people like Yuri and me whether
that's safe for them and I hope that
they can figure out how to make it safe
because as we've been very clear about
this this is a matter of global
importance anything else to add rewind
called poses the lab leak of offices to
join your podcasting debate this podcast
room fit couldn't be very good I agree
okay let's see if the virus is mutating
why is it important to know its origin
and my
mutate enough that its origin may never
be known well I'd say with this with
respect to the second there's no reason
that its current mutations and mind you
it's not an it
it's many strains and one of them could
mutate so dramatically that it's I don't
know conceivably hard to connect to
other things but given that we're
tracking it that won't happen without
our awareness but even so we have
samples from what it looked like very
early in the pandemic so there's really
there's no way it can hide there's just
a simple question of what the evidence
is about what it is most closely
associated with and the fact that
different components map to different
origin populations as a conspicuous fact
not impossible to explain through a
natural process but difficult to explain
especially in light of the absence of
any ecological connection between
different hosts that would make it
likely so anyway it we're in a landscape
that's actually the tools are well
understood they're the tools of the
scientific method and I see nothing
special about this other other than the
fact that it is so politically charged
anything you want to add yeah and I
think we've covered it here too I mean
at the very least preventing this from
happening again is justification enough
for chasing this all the way to the
bottom so there it is okay somebody
wants to know about the Gaia hypothesis
that's not directly relevant here
[Music]
how connected are the Wuhan scientists
to the global research community
wouldn't other parties be aware of what
they were working on from similar labs
Yuri you want to take that sure
highly connected probably as connected
as it could be they're just two leading
centers of coral biology in the world
Luhan is by being one and the others
barek lab and UNC and they collaborating
quite you know closely there was a
conference in Wuhan I think almost every
year there was one in 2018 there's this
nice picture of everybody including Roth
IRA can choose daily and walk my
conference this shot called it and so
they're very well connected into the yes
the world community and I'm sure that
you know behind closed doors people talk
about you know what they've been
planning to do oh they have been doing
and have awareness of things that have
been unpublished or were the research
direction they were planning to take
biggie years down the road and also the
actual postdocs that you know work in
one lab that switched into a different
lab they don't know the internal kitchen
but I think there's a bit of the
internal scientific code that you don't
snitch on your supervisors and
colleagues it's because you know that
it's the whole community the whole field
of biology gain-of-function research is
going to take a huge hit financially or
whatever if this is indeed proven to be
a lively hypothesis so nobody has any
motivation to speak out or even if they
can suspect anything
there's no they don't have anything to
gain we speak
this is my understanding maybe maybe I'm
wrong so you have a different view
correct yeah no I think I mean I think
people should look for themselves and
you can just see what the coverage of
Jiujiang Lee is you know she's given a
TED talk these two labs are connected
URI and his medium article does a great
job of pointing out what the friendly
competition between these laboratories
look like but it's a very small
community and actually this goes to this
next question on the list why won't
international biologists support an
investigation which i think is the same
question in some sense I'm gonna say
something very nasty I've seen it from
the inside and this is a major threat to
our ability to think clearly about
scientific matters the problem is that
scientists have been turned into
salesmen in order to get your research
funded you have to portray it in a light
that it is very important and that
you're in the best position to do it and
you end up saying a lot of things in
order to get your grant funded that
actually an objective analysis probably
wouldn't support and then you have these
little networks of people most people
cannot evaluate a grant by a viral
adjust about gain-of-function research
so the people who are doing the analysis
of the of the claims are involved in the
same work so a they're predisposed to
see the work as similarly important and
belittle reciprocity networks develop
and so people are funding each other's
grants and supporting their claims and
what it results in is science that is
increasingly just disconnected from
reality where you can't tell whether or
not something is really promising or is
really dangerous because the people who
are in the best position to tell you
that have a conflict of interest so what
we're seeing is what happens when you
don't protect science from conflicts of
interest the most important thing that a
scientist can have is the ability to
tell you what's actually going on even
when it isn't good for them to say so
that is a vital capacity and we are
destroying it by
the market of the market adjusts the way
science abzan flows the market is too
closely connected to science and it is
turning our scientists into huxter's and
we gotta cut it out I mean what has to
happen in order for us to see the danger
yes it's a great point for all of
science actually not just biology
because there's this huge conflict of
interests and this internal Boys Club
being reciprocity you know being in the
center of all these relations where I
submit a grant you're gonna be the
reviewer for my grand you know be nice
to me it's you and these kind of self
perpetuating decades of grant funding
being spent and sometimes as a research
that is not basically it's done at a
much slower pace than it's good because
it's just much more comfortable to do it
slowly because you know you're gonna get
next grant to the next grant maybe you
could have done it and maybe one or two
studies you or sometimes in client to
great will be spread out for 5 years
longer let's see it's a much bigger
issue if you have scientific funding
it's it's a very good model at this
point but probably better than whatever
was available you know decades centuries
brighter but still I think it could be
better to properly align the incentives
scientists be still on the cutting edge
to be honest and to be you know not
afraid to to challenge the group think
that sometimes it's very present in some
fields absolutely ok next question is it
possible that the Chinese themselves did
not know initially that it had leaked
you'd think they would have acted sooner
now my my sense is I'm not sure what I
would expect them to do because you have
to think about what these things look
like as they emerge
right you get some cluster of pneumonias
maybe somebody in a hospital thinks is
there something going on but maybe 3/4
of the time that somebody says is there
something going on it doesn't go any
farther than that or it turns out to be
just an anomalous cluster of cases that
are unrelated right and then in order to
test so how often do you want a doctor
who thinks am i seeing an unusual
phenomenon here that could be an
outbreak of something new how often do
you want that to trigger a search for a
viral particle that might be causing it
and then from there let's say okay
you've got a spate of men ammonia's and
then you find a viral particle you
haven't seen before are the two
connected that's a difficult piece of
research to do right there so I think
the point is that there are so many
steps in establishing what's going on
before you pull the the emergency break
that you don't necessarily want every
time some cluster of something emerges
for the emergency brake on global travel
to be pulled for example right we we set
the bar somewhere else because if we did
that then we'd be pulling the emergency
brake all the time and it would be for
nothing so I don't know what this looked
like inside of China I know that in
retrospect and from the outside it looks
like they moved way too late and I think
there's a lot to hold them responsible
for in that regard but if you were in
charge of building a system for figuring
out you know when to pull the emergency
brake and what to do next
I think you'd begin to recognize how
complex a problem that actually is and
this is where being proactive and
creating an environment in which things
are less primed to spread would probably
be a wiser investment I'm very curious
to hear what you think about that area
I think I agree with most of the points
probably everything you said kind of
back to the original question I think
it's very possible that yes the Chinese
themselves
I mean it's some higher level of Chinese
government themselves they didn't
realize what had happened and maybe they
were misled by kind of the local
government because we we kind of know
that the local woman government was
denying there was any kind of outbreak
and then the Beijing had to actually
step in and I think that actually
removed some of the local leaders and
reprimanded others and initially I think
it was the idea of the local government
to kind of quell down all the mention of
the potential human outbreak it was the
local authorities who were I think
targeting that dr. Lee I think the the
whistleblower the initial person who
blew the whistle in the morning is in
WeChat let her actually succumb to SARS
cough - but then kind of the the big
federal government stepped in and maybe
they were already painted in a corner
where they couldn't really admit even if
there was a lab leak hypothesis they
couldn't admit and there was one because
you know saving face or whatever but
they initially were it's highly possible
they were misled by local authorities
and the actions of the federal
government kind of hint that they were
extremely unhappy with the handling of
what the local government did and/or the
management of the Wuhan instead of
Radiology precisely because they
instituted this Major General Chan as
the head of the biology who is she's a
military biologist and she overtook the
leadership of the of the Warren
Institute I think that's a big red flag
that kind of the government the Beijing
government was very unhappy with what
had gone on or how it was handled in the
lab how the previous work was handled or
how they our break was portrayed or data
was shared with the world or whatever
but obviously the actions that they took
the Chinese federal government I think
indicative of unhappiness so yeah I
think we address this this question yep
of course we don't know any potential
potential deeper details
only time will tell yep boy I wouldn't a
little bit of transparency be wonderful
even yeah sorry and like not to deliver
the point but the the thing that they
did close who hand they still allow the
Chinese in your celebrations to go on
even though it was I think at that point
pretty clear that there's something bad
going on that's a big big Mis mistake I
think for both local and the federal
government which is probably costing you
want lives you know fine sighs well
hindsight is apparently not 20/20
because we're in the midst of making the
very same mistake here in the US where
we have suddenly decided that some
groups are creating a a hazard of viral
spread by protesting and other groups
are not which is a very odd situation so
as we yeah I saw this kind of one
California County saying that big
gatherings are limited to ten people
it's a protest and 100 is alone
something like completely illogical well
it's even worse than that
it depends what you're protesting is the
problem and that there's just no
argument for this so I agree obviously a
gathering of more than ten people if
it's a protest doesn't make it any safer
we don't know how safe it actually is
because as we've talked about before it
doesn't seem to spread outdoors as I've
also mentioned before I predict that
that will change and it will get it will
evolve to be better at spreading
outdoors so we should be very careful
about things like large gatherings but
the political double standard in terms
of who we're going to shame for
protesting in the midst of a pandemic is
it's kind of mind-blowing to see it
all right hmm what can we do to clear
yeah go ahead sorry in terms of maybe
not learning the lessons many countries
are probably opening up too early
including Russia probably or well in at
least Moscow because Russia is very
heterogeneous in different places some
places didn't have any anybody six so
they didn't even have a quarantine but
Russia
I mean Moscow had I think it was like
almost 300,000 people infected but
Moscow completely lifted all travelers
crucial restrictions last week and now
they were actually opening up some
outdoor cafes and restaurants and next
week they go to fully open all
restaurants and maybe it's a bit too
early because we still get like 1500
daily new infected in Moscow whereas you
here in Beijing and I think they had
some traces of kovat of stars to in in a
fish market and they completely shutting
down the whole city so the kind of the
difference in approach is very I think
it is sort of that maybe you know there
now the Chinese are taking it much more
seriously than the rest of the world yes
I agree with this New Zealand seems to
have cured its problem providing a model
for what we should have done but the
whole thing is just so incoherent that
really if you're gonna open back up
before the thing is stamped out or under
control or you have a vaccine the
obvious thing that you need is
ubiquitous highly reliable testing so
that we can just simply take those who
are in a position to spread the thing
and eliminate them from a position to do
it and we just we aren't there we have
really cruddy testing it's not widely
available and so anyway I find the
entire response so incoherent is to be
just absolutely maddening and we're
playing with fire we don't know what
this thing is going to become we don't
we don't even know what it is we don't
know that if it hides in some tissues
and recurs if you can get it multiple
if it gives you lasting damage that
knocks decades off your life we don't
know so anyway we're playing with fire
yes okay what can we do to create safe
spaces necessary to be able to examine
uncomfortable data not safety from a
fence but safety from having your life
destroyed for giving offense of making
an error this is what science is
supposed to be this is what science is
supposed to be and the fact that it
isn't that tells you that we have a
sickness that has no name we have lost
our greatest asset which is a scientific
apparatus that is capable of telling us
what we need to know rather than what we
want to hear and I don't know how we
create that in the current environment
because market forces are so dominant
and are subscribing to them as something
like a religion has caused us to turn
something as important as science over
to this thing that is incapable of
managing it properly but we must if we
are to navigate with the kind of power
that is now at our disposal we need a
scientific community that is tolerant of
all viable hypotheses irrespective of
what they might imply something to add
okay Yuri mentioned there was some sort
of tag that could be used to detect if
the fern site was still present in a
culture could you elaborate on how that
mechanism works is it commonly used
Thanks the way your insight is coded for
in the new nucleotide sequence the two
arginines
are coded for base the codons that are
recognized like the sequence of the
kodos is weaker than recognized with
what's called base digestion enzymes and
there are dozens hundreds of different
digestion ends
that are essentially same as can Furion
as an ensign for recognizing and cutting
protein sequences digestion enzymes are
enzymes that recognize a nucleotide
sequence and cut it and they're used for
all sorts of genetic recombination or
whatever sorts of purposes that bacteria
or other organisms have you know
invented them for but for modern biology
genetic manipulation tools we we now
kind of were able to use the them
further for our purposes which is you
can slice in a given spot of the
nucleotide sequence using the digestion
enzyme so there's a particular enzyme
recognition sequence and you put that
enzyme and culture and it will cut at
that particular spot whatever you use it
be given and so this view inside has one
particular recognition sequence that can
be recognized by what is called the 401
restriction enzyme and so if you do you
can use it as a screening tool in
culture for what is called because our
flip method of screening is the
restriction fragment length polymorphism
so basically the different lengths of
fragments that will show up on your if
you run a gel for your experiment
whereas you know if you didn't have that
that that enzyme site you'd have a one
long kind of strategy but if you have it
in your culture it will be cut so you
have two short fragments so this is the
the different length then that's the
polar motions that is used to be able to
screen for presence or absence of this
cutting site I hope I didn't confuse
you're much better at explaining things
that I am well any I mean your comments
or supported us let me I mean you're of
course working across a language barrier
you're obviously fluent but it is not
your first language so and this is tough
material to let's put it this way let's
say that you had a special kind of
scissor that cut it cut up a book only
where it found a particular sequence of
letters and you could point it at any
book and it would divide the book into
all of the fragments between that series
of letters wherever it shows up so let's
say you took the sequence of letters
meta and you had every book cut up at
every place that meta showed up in the
text well that would create a lot of
fragments of arbitrary size you could
then separate those fragments from each
other by doing something like running
them up a gel putting an electromagnetic
force at one end of a gel and then the
the fragments would migrate some
distance the bigger the fragment the
slower they would move so that they
would separate themselves out and you
would get strata you could look for a
strata that had a target l'ainte
sequence so if there was a particular
you were trying to figure out whether or
not you had a particular paragraph right
whose length you knew because meta
appears here and meta appears there so
you know what fragment you're looking
for you run these things out to get them
to separate and then you can see whether
or not you have a fragment of the
correct length right now there's a lot
of technical detail in how it is that
you calibrate these things so you know
what length you're actually looking at
but nonetheless it can be done and what
that means then is if you introduce this
site into a viral genome in order to you
know if you're introducing the fern site
for your own purposes you want the fern
site there to enhance transmissibility
then you've created by adding this
flanking sequence you've created a a
target fragment that you can then search
for and detect whether it is present or
not is that about right Yuri yeah
absolutely and then you can screen for
colonies for either the presence of this
fragment or the absence of this tracker
yeah so you can screen anything for a
fragment that's this length and then if
you want to do further scrutinizing you
can actually take what
was run to that place on the gel and you
could investigate further what's in it
but the quick and dirty test is just is
there a fragment of the right length
right and the use of these fragments in
biology was much more prevalent before
you know the whole genome sequencing or
NGS was much more cheap and you know a
little boy as it is right now whereas
before you know sequencing could take
much longer you wouldn't be able to
sequence frequently because it was
expensive but using these kind of
methods like our flip was just quick and
dirty way of screening colonies and
today it's not as prevalent using this
method because you can pretty much
sequence any calling you have but it
could still be you in use a very robust
method for if you have a very large
library quick access to it to be able to
tell if you got the wrong right calling
you or the wrong quality it's definitely
having that sequence in is definitely
helpful and it's just odd because the
codons coding for this art for the our
genes and creating this fear inside this
digestion enzymes site they're very rare
codons that they're not usually used in
coronaviruses of the power this lineage
of coronaviruses usually are Genizah
coded differently so it's just odd to
see and it's like to exact same codons
very rare kodos in in sequence so that's
just odd coincidence yeah it was human
made make all the total sense so if i
can sum this up there are lots of little
techniques that people who are skilled
in the laboratory arts use to make their
own work simpler right just the same way
a programmer would put out in a little
piece of code that would allow them to
check whether some subroutine was doing
what it was supposed to or something
like that there are lots of little
tricks you can put a little you can add
something that will cause a particle to
flourish
if it's present and so then you can just
you know shine a particular light at a
colony and see whether the thing is
there that sort of thing these things
are everywhere these little techniques
that just facilitate laboratory work and
so what URI is saying is that to code
for arginine is common but the way
arginine is coded the particular codon
that is found in this particular
sequence next to the fern site is
conspicuous in that it is absent from
most coronaviruses so for whatever
reason coronaviruses don't produce it
normally or not very regularly and right
at a site that we're talking about how
did this a why is there for insight
that's uncommon and conspicuous B why is
it an insert rather than a series of
mutations and then see why does it have
this conspicuous sequence next to it
that has an own use in the lab and that
is coded for in a way that does not
suggest a normal natural process in
these viruses because in general we
don't see it that's three pieces of
evidence related to the fern site that
don't it's not the smoking gun but it's
certainly conspicuous that somebody
working in a lab facilitating their own
work might have added this sequence in
order to be able to cut at that exact
location and done it in a way that fit
their laboratory modality rather than
some sort of natural process yep perfect
all right let's see what do you think
about the full full of misinformation
World Health Organization link under
every video even mentioning the virus I
get the problem you got a lot of
misinformation you've got a lot of
people spreading low quality conspiracy
hypotheses on the other hand Google
doesn't know what a counterintuitive
hypothesis that is important sounds like
it doesn't have an algorithm to figure
it out it doesn't have a team of
who are capable of sweating it out and
even if it did that team of biologists
is gonna suffer from the same kind of
perverse incentives that are virality
community is suffering from so in some
sense I think the only rational thing
you want to do is leave it so that yes
cruddy information can be presented
people are in a position to evaluate it
themselves but that means that the ideas
that people want to shut down but that
are correct are also allowed to to get
into the world I just don't see an
alternative system at this point so I'm
very much against these warnings because
I think they basically are a wink that
says this is not a sanctioned idea and
this is not a sanctioned idea yes we'll
eliminate a lot of garbage but it will
also eliminate the stuff that the system
doesn't want to hear the true stuff that
the system doesn't want to hear anything
that you want to prevent misinformation
and I guess having this kind of generic
warning is much better weighted
censorship I guess there's no really
like a win-win situation in this
emerging pandemic a lot of unknown
emerging knowledge that we still don't
know they could the truth value of so
eventually everything will be sorted out
and we shouldn't definitely shouldn't
censor or let stop anyone from prevent
anybody from speaking having some sort
of warning you know all these ideas are
still in stages yep okay next one given
Derek's paper posits a bat from Malaysia
as possible source what is the
relationship between the Wuhan CDC which
collects bats and the Wuhan Institute of
virality which works on bat borne
viruses amongst them amongst others
I must say I don't totally understand
the question there parts of it I get to
you do you understand the question I
think I I'm a so there's I think of
two-part questions really two-part
question because I mean there is this
recent print by - I can others from ABS
already in his published paper that did
posit that it's probably the start
students probably came from Malaysia
because pangolins are only found in
Malaysia and but again it's just a
conjecture I mean they don't really have
any any solid evidence to back up that
claim and the the second part of the
question is the relationship between the
guqin CDC there was like 300 meters from
the Hunan cmart seafood market and the
Mohan Institute of biology because there
was this
original idea by the Chinese scientists
I think Michelle buteau who published a
preprint and and thought that maybe it
was someone working from someone working
in the woman CDC close to the seafood
market it has an advert in advertently
released the kind of sample of bat
coronavirus
or maybe arthropod coronavirus bat
related kind of virus found in north
report because this was young one cow or
something and he's he's a big guy he he
is investigating bat worn ticks and so
he had been featured prominently in some
Chinese publications where he was
showing collecting bats finding ticks on
them bringing bringing those live bats
and ticks back into the Wuhan CDC to
collect to extract the samples to
extract the core virus and I think he
boasted that he had been quarantined
sometimes because he was exposed bath
bladder but
urine and so this was the original idea
of this change dr. shalba tell that
maybe he is the guy who caused the
outbreak but they don't show up at our
cool that preprint and can
this light of an investigation of the
ones DC being the possible origin of the
lab leak it kind of died down and the
one Institute of biology took the center
stage but the coming back to the
question there is a very close-knit
relationship actually between the two
institutions because first of all
there's many scientists that seem to
have double affiliation they kind of
work in in one and in the other
sometimes they do work in in CGC
sometimes they do work in WRV and also
there was collaboration in the one CDC
bringing live animals and extracting
samples of various viruses which they
would then turn over to the biology for
further work or analysis so there's and
there's been a lot of investigation
online of looking into this one CDC
what's going on there because they were
actually in the process of moving from
that spot near the seafood market to
somewhere more remote location and they
actually had I think a public tender up
on their website
back in September that they had a huge
pile of like toxic waste they needed to
get rid of and so and there was a fire
in the company that was later turned out
that they won the this kind of the
contracts for clearing out the toxic
waste so this but like too many very
interesting things going on that I must
admit I have been following very closely
but the Oakland CDC and it's connection
to first saw all their live animals
being kept there and second to the the
Arth report vectors that she gently
actually tried to distance ourselves
from when she was describing her
database and everybody's there's a lot
of like potential for questions that
still we should still get answer because
you know dicks are found in bats and
you're still gonna take outbreak in the
past few years with Lyme disease and
other diseases and while tics haven't
been found to carry corona viruses they
have been found to carry closely related
viruses in particular by actually by
this person
drink one cow from from the Wuhan CDC
who actually had a paper on like the
whole history of or the whole host of
fire is scary' by by takes bad word
antics and and there was I think another
article in Bank Olympics this was just
one area of research that I kind of gave
up on way back when looking into takes
another arthropod mosquitoes maybe
whether they could be the source of
either the natural source of the corona
virus or source to the leak maybe you
know the in fact it's a lab animal and
carried it out of the facility but I
just completely give up on that line of
questioning maybe someone can pick it up
and yeah I must say echo logically
something like a tick is much more
plausible to me than something like a
Pangolin I mean even if it was a
Pangolin a something like a tick that
could transmit it between a bat and the
Pangolin would would make more sense
than some other mechanism am i right -
the Wuhan CDC does not do
gain-of-function research but I think
their lab is bsl-2 only so but again I
haven't looked into it and actually
scrub the they all it mentioned from
their website and once the DCC of that
location and actually changed the
location of the one CDC on Google Maps
and my doing whatever from the one near
to the seafood market to probably the
new building to which they were planning
to move to it's much closer to they were
gonna see the world crosser
yep but I mean I'm sure people from the
lab if they probably engaged in some
sort of gain-of-function research
because they were also affiliated with a
180 over neurology but they wouldn't do
it like in that location they would have
done it probably be in the 108 stove I
Raji but they could have of course
tracked back and forth whatever
contamination they could have been
contaminated with between yep
all right we have just a few more here
another argument for gain-of-function
research is being certain that we really
do understand how a virus becomes
infectious and which things affect its
infectivity yeah that's certainly true I
mean you can do it retrospectively if we
found a virus for example in a new human
virus related bat virus we can look at
you know what exact new taejun's the
receptor binding domain caused this but
then actually to do it proactively to
take some bad born virus and try to make
it infect for humans to me that's
completely counterintuitive it doesn't
make any sense why would you want to do
this again is already a little bit too
many times there are a huge uncountable
number of variations that could happen
in nature manual which could make a
virus you know human born but never will
happen in nature in trying to recreate
it in the lab yeah I agree it seems like
if you're gonna do this sort of research
you could have a model system that
actually was far from humans and you
could study infectivity in the model
system I mean maybe this is done I don't
know but you're right the real danger is
from increasing infectivity in humans or
in human tissue in order to study the
process in order to prevent an infection
of humans there's an obvious hazard
that's going to be almost impossible to
get around unless you could figure out a
kill switch or something so that nothing
could possibly escape because it wasn't
viable absent some component that you
controlled yeah it's a good point
because they do this in pseudo viruses
and there's actually been a lot of this
kind of research where it's not only
true gain-of-function research where you
create a live virus with it human
receptor binding to me you can do it in
the super virus where you put the
receptor binding domain and they're
completely unrelated virus which
wouldn't be able to be viable in its own
I mean it could
in fact human cells and you can then see
it in a lab setting but if it escapes it
wouldn't be able to propagate in a
normal setting yeah why I mean it's it's
a limited of course because it's not our
true virus it's that's why it's called
pseudo virus but I think for research
purposes it's good enough that you don't
need to really go and to exponentially
more risk and actually generate life
iris there's more infectious humans that
was originally in the original holes yep
the problem with a kill switch is of
course it can evolve away and the
evolutionary pressure would be for it to
evolve away so you would have to build
it very carefully so that the room for
it to evolve away didn't exist it has to
really stop dead in its tracks at the
point that you're not fueling it in
order for that to work but anyway it's a
theoretical possibility and for all I
know it's happening in some way that I
don't know I'm not aware of but alright
let's see another argue Oh what is your
opinion of Professor Michael Levitz
findings regarding how the response to
kovat 19 should have and should be
handled are you aware of this of what
this is about
yeah I have a feeling shortly after we
end the stream I'm going to realize what
this is about or run across it and kick
myself for not having a good answer but
I don't all right what is your opinion
on Kary Mullis the inventor of the PCR
test who passed in August 2019
I must say I didn't know that he had
died if that's what that means stating
the PCR test should not be used to
diagnose disease see questioning the HIV
AIDS hypothesis 30 years of descent do
you have thoughts well I know those
people have been drawing parallels
between years of the both Nobel
laureates who have since started
expressing questionable ideas other than
that I mean
I don't know just cuz ya like person has
done good work previously doesn't mean
they're right today conversely just
because you know their opinion might be
not popular you might not be supported
by because mainstream orthodoxy doesn't
mean they're wrong yeah hot water with
other Nobel laureates which have been
mentioned today I won't it's very very
at this point very dangerous territory
going to yes I won't in terms of the PCR
being able to not that shouldn't be used
for diagnosing disease I think it's
wrong absolutely wrong why not I mean
it's it's a great tool that have been
used by in many viruses to confirm
there's yep
I would say you know in Kary Mullis case
obviously quite brilliant a little crazy
and my sense is it might be that a
certain a certain amount of crazy
combined with brilliance combined with a
whole hell of a lot of luck so you don't
get killed off in the process of getting
your credential might make you more
likely to make an important discovery
like PCR but then it might mean that
you're more likely to come up with
things that have important kind of
currency but aren't right like the idea
that HIV is not the causal agent in AIDS
and this is what I conclude it and I
think I said somewhere previously the
thing about concluding that HIV doesn't
cause AIDS is AIDS is a syndrome a
syndrome is downstream of a failure in
this case many things can cause that
failure and something that sometimes
causes that failure cannot do it in
certain circumstances because
you're in a complex system so we should
actually expect that the two things that
I think set Kary Mullis off in this case
one that not everybody with HIV gets
AIDS and two that not everybody with
AIDS has detectable HIV you would expect
those things just by virtue of the fact
that the syndrome is downstream of
something that could be triggered in
multiple ways so what that means is we
have to change our mechanism for
investing investigating complex systems
because a simple falsification 'us
to - Occam's razor doesn't work not
because it isn't philosophically right
but because complex systems tend to
falsify every hypothesis by virtue of
the fact that there are lots of
processes interfacing with each other so
I don't know how much farther to go with
that but I do think well let's just
let's just leave it at that
Melissa's a brilliant guy who
contributed tremendously and I think we
have to take seriously what he says but
it doesn't make him right and in this
case I think he's wrong okay last
question to avoid problems with kill
switches why not genetically engineer a
super smart slave species that can
conduct gain-of-function experimentation
on unpopular human subjects no lab leaks
well that's a terrible suggestion I'm
sorry I read it out loud I'm pretty sure
it's a joke but damn if you're gonna
make a joke you got to include an emoji
that's the thing that's how we know for
sure
okay well URI is there anything you want
to say in closing not really just want
to thank you for organizing these chats
had a lot of fun doing it thanks again
yeah thank you I hope you you bring on
more guests or much more qualified than
I to answer the viola G questions and
explore this hypothesis for low angles
not necessarily from the we've explored
I mean if maybe Anderson won't come on
to your podcast and defend why he thinks
virtually zero chances of being lovely
the great debate yep I agree all right
well thanks Thank You Yuri a pre future
your work and your dedication to this
question and I hope we find out
something interesting soon and that
would be a great excuse to have you back
all right thanks everybody
appreciate the questions please like and
subscribe
pass this around if you thought it was
interesting and see you next time
[Music]
you